Okay, good morning. Haven't done one of these live streams in quite
a while. Been a
good year or so. Let me stop this.
Sorry,
excuse me for a minute.
Let
me see.
Look. Looking. Okay, these controls. Sometimes I'm doing things different. I'm going
to see. I think that's it. I think I
know what you do with that. With that? Is that? Looking? Okay,
these controls. Sometimes I'm doing things different. I'm going to see. I
think that's it. I think I know what you do with that.
With that? Is that? Trying to do something with the audio recording,
so I'm going to start now so as not to
keep
everyone waiting even longer.
I'll do a recording.
Okay. If you get that up there that'd be great, if not,
it will suffice whatever recording you do and this live stream. Alright,
anyway, so today's דף daf is ט"ז. tet-zayin. We are picking up
like a good call it 10 lines from the bottom of the
previous עמוד, amud, so בעי אילפא. ba'i ilfa. See that? בעי אילפא,
ba'i ilfa, the last word on my recording for that.
So בעי אילפא, ba'i ilfa, ידיים טהורות לחצאין או אין טהורות לחצאין,
yadayim tehorot lachata'in o ein tehorot lachata'in, which seems to be the
equivalent of can someone be like a little bit pregnant? Like, can
hands be like half טהור tahor or not? So obviously the question
is what do we mean by that? היכי דמי? heichi dami? So
what kind of case would this be? אילימא דקמשי בי תרי מרביעית.
ileima d'kamoshi bei terei meriviit.
So two, let's say you have two people and they're trying to
both wash their hands from one כלי kli that's holding
a רביעית. reviit. רביעית טוב. reviit tuv. So that can't be the
question. We know the answer to that. ותנן, vehatnan, מרביעית נוטלין לידיים
לאחד אפילו לשנים. meriviit notlin yadayim leachad afilu lishnayim. So you're allowed
to. One person can do it, even two people can do it.
So that's not the question. Why would he ask something we know
already? אלא דקמשי חדא חדא ידיה. ella d'kamoshi chada chada yadei. So
he's doing sort of like one hand at a time. But ותנן,
vehatnan, נטל ידו אחת בנטילה ואחת בשטיפה ידיו טהורות.
natal yado achat b'netila
veachat b'shtifa yadei tehorot. So that won't be the question either, because
we've answered that as well.
There's something called שטיפת ידיים, shtifat yadayim, something called נטילת ידיים. netilat
yadayim. So נטילת ידיים netilat yadayim would be what we do, you
know, you take
the cup, whatever, you know, pour it from whatever is in the
contents of that vessel onto your hands, but you can also do
a
שטיפה, shtifa, like let's say you're at the ocean, you have no
cup, or you're by a river, just like dunk your hands in
in the water. So what ברכה bracha do you make on that?
Seems to be that the, at least what I've looked into it,
is the, there's a while ago, that the answer is you still
would say נטילת ידיים, netilat yadayim, at least according to עובדיה יוסף.
Ovadia Yosef. I'm not sure what the אשכנזים Ashkenazim would say, but
I would say you would say שטיפת ידיים, shtifat yadayim, but I
think it's really kind of a מחלוקת machloket thing, נטילת ידיים. netilat
yadayim. But you can do that, you know, like can you do
things in like snow, whatever. It's not snowing yet, so we'll wait
for that one.
But yes, wait for the snow to melt first for years.
So anyway, but you know, even if you do one with נטילה
netila and one with שטיפה, shtifa, it would work. So presumably, you
know, if you do one hand at a time with נטילה, netila,
it would certainly work. אלא דקמשי פלגא פלגא דידיה.
ella d'kamoshi palga
palga d'yadei. So sort of, like why you'd do this I don't
know, but the question would be that like he sort of like
did it like half your hand at a time. You know, you
wash half your hand, you sort of dried it, then you wash
the other
part
of your hand. So you know, you end up making your whole
hand טהורות tehorot for the purpose of נטילת ידיים, netilat yadayim, so
you end up washing your whole hand but you did it in
stages. So that's the question. But and he wouldn't be asking that
either. והאמר דבי רבי ינאי ידיים אין טהורות לחצאין. vehamar d'vei Rabbi
Yannai yadayim ein tehorot lachata'in. So it doesn't work. Right? So you
can't do these half measures. So he's not asking that either. So
what is he asking? No, לא צריכא דאיכא משקה טופח. lo tzericha
d'ika mashkeh tofeach.
So it's sort of like a little moist. So meaning he didn't
fully dry your hand,
meaning you still did it in stages but you didn't fully dry
your hand in stage one to stage two. It was still a
little moist, so then the question is, you know, can the moistness
of your quote-unquote dried hand combine with the wetness of your second
washing to make them all together as if you've washed them all
at once? Whatever it amounts to. לא צריכא דאיכא, lo tzericha d'ika,
no I did that. והיכא דאיכא משקה טופח מאי הוי? vechi d'ika
mashkeh tofeach mai havai? So what? Who cares if it's a little
moist? ותנן, vehatnan, הניצוק והקטפרס ומשקה טופח אינו חיבור לא לטומאה ולא
לטהרה. hanitzok vehakatrafes umashkeh tofeach eino chibur lo l'tuma velo l'tahara. So
basically, these are ways of doing it, like let's say it's complete,
you know, if it's pouring or if it's sort of like, you
know, on a slope or
all these sort of things, doesn't work. Not for טומאה, tuma, not
for טהרה. tahara. So like,
for instance, let's say you have two כלים kelim and you're pouring
from one to another, one is טמא tamei and one is
טהור. tahor. to a
טמא tamei. *Tame* כלי *Kli* or does it or vice versa, the
טמא tamei *Tame* כלי *Kli* become טהור tahor *Tahor* because it's connected
to
a טהור tahor. *Tahor* כלי *Kli*? So it doesn't work. It doesn't
do anything.
So he wouldn't be asking that either. So no, let's use כי
איכא טופח להטפיח *Ki Ika Tofeach Lehatfiach*. Okay, so it's not just
like a little moist, rather it's like really wet still. It's wet
enough of like did a really poor job drying your hands. Not
like 100% wet, not like dripping and wet,
but if I put my hands on something else, that'd be wet
enough to get something else wet. So again, I'm not pouring it
all at the same time, but it's still very, very wet
on the first part of the hands.
And it could be dripping, whatever, but the point is I didn't
wash it both at the same time, both parts of my hand
or whatever at the same time. So that's the question. דתנן נטילת
ידיים טופח
להטפיח חיבור *Detnan Netilat
Yadayim Tofeach Lehatfiach
Chibur*. So we also haven't answered to that, that it does work.
So what is he asking? No, so דלמא אינון מקוואות *Dilma Inun
Mikvaot*. So no, maybe that's just like a מקווה *Mikvah* question,
but not a ידיים *Yadayim* question, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, and it would be the opinion of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? *Rabbi Yehuda*. And what is that that we're referring
to? דתנן מקווה שיש בו ארבעים סאה מכוונות וירדו שניים וטבלו שניהם
בבת אחת טהורים *Detnan Mikvah Sheyesh Bo Arbayim Seah Mechuvannot Veyardu Shnayim
Vetavlu Shneyhem Bevat Achat Tehorim*. So let's say of a מקווה *Mikvah*
that has exactly directly its שיעור Shiur *Shiur*. And then two people
go in and are טובלו *Tovlu*. So if they both go in
at the same time, then that's fine because they're both dunking in
a kosher מקווה *Mikvah*. זה אחר זה *Ze Achar Ze* now what
would be the problem if it's done consecutively?
Some water's going to stick to the first guy. So it wouldn't
be exactly thirty-nine it wouldn't be exactly forty סאה *Seah* for the
other guy, maybe 39 point whatever it is. So he doesn't have
enough. So what do you do? Does it work? Does it not
work? ראשון טהור tahor, והשני טמא tamei? *Rishon Tahor Vehasheni Tame*. So
that's what the תנא קמא Tana Kamma, *Tanna Kamma* says, it only
works for the first guy, because the second guy hasn't been in
enough מקווה *Mikvah* water so to speak. אבל רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
אומר אם היו רגליו של ראשון נוגעות במים אף השני טהור Tahor,
*Aval Rabbi Yehuda Omer Im Hayu Raglav Shel Rishon Nogot Bamayim Af
Hasheni Tahor*. But if the first guy is still not fully out
of the מקווה *Mikvah*, let's say his feet are at the edge
of
the lip of the מקווה *Mikvah* or whatever it is and his
toes are like in the water still, then he can be viewed
as a חיבור *Chibur*. So whatever water from the מקווה *Mikvah* is
on the first guy, so he's connected to the מקווה *Mikvah*. So
there's still enough.
So it'd be fine. So that'd be the opinion of anyway, that's
the point is, when we said it's חיבור *Chibur*, maybe that's a
מקווה *Mikvah* question. We don't know if it's a question for נטילת
ידיים *Netilat Yadayim* what the answer for that is. So that's what
he's asking. All right, so let's see what he's asking.
So we didn't answer
it, but anyway potentially at least we can most likely say it
might go according to party lines, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
would agree in the ידיים *Yadayim* question he'd be טהור Tahor. *Tahor*
and the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* would not.
So yeah, I mean it doesn't seem to me that we answered
it.
I don't know what the law is. But what I do know
is what we tried to do is that regarding that first part,
you actually could, so it's more of an עניין *Inyan* that the
כלי *Kli* have a רביעית *Reviit*. It has to be like a
kosher כלי *Kli* having the represented amount. As to how many people
can do it, you actually could have two people doing it at
the same time from one כלי *Kli* רביעית *Reviit*, so too if
for yourself, and it's a רביעית *Reviit*, so half go to the
one hand, half go to the other. It's not like you're getting
a full רביעית *Reviit* on each hand. But what we try to
do is have a full רביעית *Reviit* on each hand to avoid
any problems. That's what we practically do. I don't know about
this
case of דדין *Dadin*, would there be any problem or not. Okay
anyway, and again it doesn't seem like we've really answered the question,
though at least we understood what it was. All right. אמר רבי
ירמיה הרי אמרו harei amru. *Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah Harei Amru* because I
think this is a separate topic now. אמר רבי ירמיה הרי אמרו
*Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah Harei Amru* which is a very interesting way of
seeing this, but they know they said הבא ראשו ורובו במים שאובים
*Haba Rosho Verubo
Bemayim Sheuvim* case one, and וטהור שנפלו על ראשו ורובו שלשה לוגים
מים שאובים *Vetahor Shenaplu Al Rosho Verubo Shlosha Lugin Mayim Sheuvim* case
two, טמא tamei, *Tame*. So if somebody, so this is a case
you're actually טהור *Tahor*, right? You dunked or either you just didn't
become טמא tamei, *Tame* or you went into a מקווה *Mikvah*. And
but then what happened was
that you went afterwards into drawn water, let's say you took a
bath after going to the
מקווה *Mikvah*, or somehow whatever it is, like drawn water got poured
on you,
same idea like I guess sort of be like you go into
like almost like a shower kind of thing, someone's pouring on you.
So טמא Tamei *Tame*. So why would that be? In other words,
you already went to a kosher מקווה *Mikvah* or you're whatever it
is, or you just didn't become טמא *Tame* from the last time
you went.
Why are we saying now you are טמא *Tame*? So the way
רש"י Rashi. *Rashi*... explained it, which is—it's like a pretty much agreed-upon
explanation—is let me just find it
in
this רש"י. Rashi
It's
like the old style, it doesn't
have
the—like in the bolded
רש"י. Rashi. טמא. התרומה עד שיטבול Ha-terumah ad she-yitbol is the first
wide line.
So you're טמא for תרומה terumah until you actually go טובל tovel
again. ומשמנה עשר דבר היא. u-mishmonah asar davar hi. So there were
these eighteen things that, you know, we learned them in the beginning
of שבת. Shabbat. There was this big מחלוקת machloket between תלמידי בית
שמאי, talmidei Beit Shammai, תלמידי בית הלל, talmidei Beit Hillel,
and בית שמאי Beit Shammai won, won out. And then even though
we have the general concept of אין גוזרין גזירה על הציבור אלא
אם כן רוב ציבור יכולין לעמוד בה, ein gozerin gezeirah al ha-tzibur
ela im ken rov tzibur yecholin la'amod bah, that you don't, you
know, try to make these גזירות gezeirot unless people can really stand
by it, these eighteen things were the exception because, you know, apparently
these were like people really felt very strongly about it from what
I remember from
that
at the time. Anyway, מפרש מאי טעמא גזרו עלה, mefaresh mai ta'ama
gozru alah, so why, why is this? Why would you become טמא?
דשהיה להם מי מערות סרוחים de-she-hayah lahem mei me'arot sruchim for טבילה.
tevilah. So you know, sort of like think of it our modern-day
analog of like going to the מקוה mikvah ערב ראש השנה, erev
Rosh Hashanah, right? Like everyone's going, you know, by the end, and
if you're not there the first time, it's like disgusting, right. So,
and they don't clean it in between. So you know, so why
I stopped going.
So, anyway, so like, you know, I mean you know, well water
can be great, but like if it's sort of like turgid water,
you know, maybe not so good. You know, ever since some cave,
you know who knows what like bear lived in there, you know,
whatever anyway, but the point is like, yeah.
So in the, a century ago, there were dozens of מקוות mikvaot
in New York City. And most of them were closed by health
department. Interesting, yeah.
But anyway, so you know they had that same problem back then,
but whatever it was, it was like, you know, really disgusting caves.
So they used to go in the מקוה mikvah ולאחר טבילה היו
רוחצים בשאובין. ve-le-achar tevilah hayu rochatzin be-she'uvin. So then they're like, you
know, this is really disgusting, so they used to then, you know,
cleanse themselves, right? Like you know in the nice place to go
to, you know, for especially women, you go to take a shower
before going to the מקוה, mikvah, then they take a shower afterwards
because they just want to cleanse themselves from all the filth and
dirt that was in the, in the cave water wherever it is
they jumped in. So then they used to say: אטו אלו מטהרין
אלו מטהרין? atu elu meta'arin elu meta'arin? So it's not the מקוה
mikvah that makes you טהור since everyone takes a shower afterwards, it's
the shower that makes you טהור. So then they said וגזרו עליהן.
ve-gozru aleihen. So then they said, alright, no good. So you know,
they don't want people thinking that, let's just skip the מקוה, mikvah,
right? Just go take the shower. So that's why they said if
you, even if you take the shower having after having gone to
the מקוה, mikvah, still no good.
And you know, so based on what has—you ever looked into a
in in contemporary times? I was told I think you have to
wait so many hours after going to the מקוה mikvah to take
a shower so that...
oh, I never heard that.
Oh, so it takes three or four hours I don't know.
It would matter if you're going to the Temple Mount, but it
wouldn't matter for husband and wife because...
no not for husband and wife. I meant like you know if
you're going before a חג chag you go to the מקוה mikvah
as a custom, okay.
That's a pure מנהג minhag anyway.
But but but I'm just, I don't know, that was just discussed
in my... right, yeah.
The only practical application of a מקוה mikvah for a man today
is if he want to go to the Temple Mount.
I see. Yeah.
Or or a convert. Yeah that's true, right.
So it's irrelevant this question about the shower.
But I mean I don't know if there's still some sort of
a vestigial, you know,
idea of waiting, I don't know. I really don't know, you know,
we'd have to ask a
רב Rav
in that respect, right. So
that was a גזירה. gezeirah. ושוב גזרו על השופך על ראשו ועל
רובו שלושה לוגין מים שאובין. ve-shuv gozru al ha-shofech al rosho ve-al
rubo sheloshah lugin mayim she'uvin. So that's if like you know go
in like you know take a take a shower. But similarly if
like you know three לוגין lugin of drawn water, drawn water fell
on this guy. דהא ומהא חדא הלכתא היא. de-ha u-me-ha chada hilcheta
hi. It's basically the same idea, right. So anyway, so
both so anyway, so what were you saying? They were גוזר gozer
on on these two things.
Now, right, if you go into, you know, שלושה לוגין sheloshah lugin
or if like some of it falls on you. So בעי רמי
בר אבא, ba'ei Rami bar Abba, it's the same thing, right. רמי
בר אבא, Rami bar Abba, חציו בשפיכה וחציו בביאה מאי? chatzyo be-shfichah
ve-chatzyo be-vi'ah mai?
So let's say half of it, you know, three לוגין, lugin, but
half of it was you know
you went into and the other half was like pouring on you
then what? Is it still have that same גזירה? gezeirah? So alright
תיקו teiku we don't know. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa הרי
אמרו. So
we also know that they said בעל קרי חולה שנתנו עליו תשעה
קבין מים
טהור.
ba'al keri choleh she-natnu alav tish'ah kabin
mayim tahor. So this we—I know this is on the books that
you know this was a תקנה, takanah, a very old תקנה takanah
actually, that
that this is תקנת
עזרא. Takanat Ezra. Let's take a step back. I mean, you know,
in order to go to the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash you definitely
have to, if you've had some sort of emission, right, whether or
not you've actually had sex or you've had emission without having had
sex, you're now a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. So now you know,
and then you have issues about going to the בית המקדש, Beit
Ha-Mikdash, right,
so fine let's say you're not going to the בית המקדש Beit
Ha-Mikdash you just want to learn תורה. Torah. So עזרא Ezra had
a תקנה takanah that even a בעל קרי ba'al keri should not
be learning, you know this תקנה... takanah... about learning about learning תורה
Torah or דאווענינג, davening, right, that you shouldn't be doing unless you
have gone to the מקוה. mikvah. That's what רש"י Rashi says over
there, בעל קרי חולה טהור, Ba'al Keri Choleh Tahor, it's somewhere in
the middle of the wide lines, דברי תורה. Divrei Torah. The עזרא
תיקן, Ezra tiken, oh wait, let me take עזרא תיקן, Ezra tiken,
all right, טבילה לבעלי קריין כדי שלא יהיו כתרנגולים. Tevilah l'Ba'ali Kerin,
k'dei shelo yehoyu k'tarnegolim. So
עזרא Ezra said that all right, before you learn תורה Torah you
need to go to the מקוה, mikvah, but והקילו על החולה, v'hikelu
al hacholeh, ונתנו תשעה קבין, v'natnu tesha kabin, אפילו שאובין. afilu shuvin.
But let's say you're sick, right, and it's you know, difficult for
you to go to the מקוה. mikvah. So then, all right, you
can basically take a shower. That's essentially what he's saying. Like you
can if you have nine קבין, kabin, which is, you know, you'll
get that much taking a shower, then you are טהור, but it's
just for a sick בעל קרי. Ba'al Keri. So if you're not
sick, then you really should still be going to the מקוה. mikvah.
Now, you know, I think we don't really say this today because,
you know, the idea was you want to approach תורה Torah with
a certain level of seriousness and not like the lightheadedness that preceded
it. So I think as far as I, and this is like,
I forgot to look this one up, but as far as I
remember, we don't really say this anymore because it's not like, you
know, we're in such a serious demeanor all the rest of the
time that, you know, meaning we're always like approaching תורה. Torah. In
some ways it's a sad commentary on where we are today, that
if we really always took it seriously then, you know, then we
would have to. But since we don't as much, so the קולא
kula is you don't have to really worry about this anymore. That's
as far as I remember.
Yes, some say this was a תקנה takkanah of עזרא Ezra that
was eventually overturned.
Yeah. Doesn't say by whom though?
So,
but, there is a note here from ריטב"א Ritva after the רש"י.
Rashi ריטב"א Ritva says indeed the pouring of nine קבין kabin does
not purify the בעל קרי. Ba'al Keri. It does, however, remove the
prohibition against תורה Torah study and prayer enacted by עזרא. Ezra.
Right, yeah, that's what I'm saying. This is for, and I'm saying
you still have to go to a מקוה mikvah to go to
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, as I was starting to say, but
at least, but he, עזרא, Ezra, had an additional stringency that you
had to, תורה Torah study. Yeah, that you couldn't even study תורה,
Torah, which for some תורה Torah scholars was a problem.
And this is why a lot of guys go to the מקוה
mikvah first thing in the morning.
And this is why, and as far as I know, regarding the
טבילה tevilah before חג, chag, I remember seeing this but I haven't
looked at this in like, I mean, literally like decades. But some
people say בדיעבד b'diavad if you don't go to the מקוה, mikvah,
take a shower, based on this idea, right,
that בדיעבד b'diavad that'd be okay also.
There used to be traditions where women who were not married would
go
to the מקוה mikvah ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. And it's
actually in codified in the קיצור שולחן ערוך. Kitzur Shulchan Aruch. Back
in Hungary, I guess, they actually did that.
So just to the question about if these men you're talking about,
Charlie, would go to the מקוה, mikvah, if they took a shower
afterwards, or if a woman after she goes to the מקוה mikvah
before she,
after having her period, is, if she takes a shower, does that
affect her?
You know, actually, I really don't,
it's the same question.
No, but as far as I know, it doesn't, you know what
I mean? But I mean, I didn't, I can't say that I
looked into that and know the answer.
Yeah, right, okay.
Yeah, it can affect her
נדה niddah status, it might
make her טמא, but that's not something we really worry about today.
בימים, b'yam, oh. Because we're not eating like, you know, stuff. We're
not eating anyway. We're all טמא מת tamei met anyway because, you
know, you have to have a אפר פרה efer parah in order
to get out of that.
The only reason she's going to the מקוה mikvah is just because
of the condition.
Because no, because the separate נדה niddah prohibition that's in the תורה
Torah and the תקנה takkanah that made it more stringent. So we
treat a woman who's menstruating like both a נדה niddah and a
זבה גדולה. zavah gedolah. Right. We put in all the stringency. But,
but that's not a טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah situation.
Right, but it
matters
in terms of relationship with her husband.
Yeah, that's only the נדה niddah and זבה zavah prohibition.
So when we say that we say that you're טמא, I mean
it's more like I think, you know, like תרומה terumah purposes in
some sense, you know what I mean?
תרומה terumah and קדשים, kodshim, neither of which matters today. I see.
And the only practical application if you want to ascend the Temple
Mount. Even today. Even today. And I asked Rabbi Linzer to, to
explain how that this should work in our times and he hasn't
got back.
That's a hot topic.
Right. So so like so and that's what רש"י Rashi said that
first wide line, טמא לתרומה עשייה בו. tamei l'terumah asiya bo. Do
you see that?
Really? This, that first wide line רש"י Rashi where he said טמא
לתרומה. tamei l'terumah. Right. That's where he's saying it's for תרומה. terumah
asiya bo. It doesn't say that that this is, you know, doesn't
immediately like reverse the fact that she went to the מקוה mikvah
in terms of being with her husband, like that's what Charlie was
saying. Right. But I mean, like, does that mean anything today? I
mean, it doesn't sound like it, right, you know. Back then when
people were, you know, eating חולין בטהרה chullin b'taharah or if you
were אשת כהן eshet kohen or if you were whatever it is,
you know, or you were going to give it to the כהן,
kohen, right, that made a big difference. But you know now we
don't have any of that, like, so to answer your question, but
you know, but again, like, since, but your question was... Since your
question was twofold, one was with the wife, I think we can
confidently say that it makes no difference, a husband and wife being
together, but she's I guess, in some abstract
sense, if you take a shower afterwards, you're טמא for תרומה Trumah
purposes or whatever that really means.
But regarding ערב חג, Erev Chag, since there's a custom to be
טהור, could you sort of undo something by then going to the
shower afterwards? I really don't know, so that's what we'd have to
ask.
רש"י specifically says she has
to
immerse herself for תרומה. Trumah. Right. But again, they can still be
together intimately for נידה Niddah purposes.
Anyway,
so then we first went on from the people in the turgid
rainwater, then to the guy who's about קרי Keri that took
a shower, right?
So he said if you're sick, then he says you're טהור. So
if רב פפא Rav Papa same idea, חציו בטבילה וחציו בנתינה מה?
Chetzo b'tvila v'chetzo b'netina mah? Let's say it's like half and half,
half of it like you went in the shower or
some of it was poured on you, some you went into, you
took a bath for half, half שיעור and then the other half
was like the shower or whatever kind of idea. תיקו. Teiku. We
don't know. All right, fine. Back to גיטין. Gittin. I am going
to, this would be easier if I diagram this part of the
משנה Mishnah
because
we're going to be referring to it.
Unfortunately, we're going to get rid of this fine artwork.
Tissue does work much better than an eraser with
tissue.
Fine. We're going to go back to the משנה Mishnah because that's
what we're going to be doing the rest of the day.
Okay, it's sort of the middle.
So אחד, Echad, so we dealt with a number of cases. So
one says בפני נכתב. Bifanay nictav. אחד
אומר בפני נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נחתם פסול. Echad omer bifanay nictav
ve-echad omer bifanay nechtam pasul.
I don't know if people can see the very end of this.
Yeah, you can. Okay. Now בפני נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נחתם פסול.
Bifanay nictav ve-echad omer bifanay
nechtam pasul.
שנים אומרים בפנינו נכתב.
Shnayim omrim bifanaynu nictav.
Now
two.
Same thing. שנים אומרים בפנינו נכתב
ואחד אומר בפני
נחתם.
Shnayim omrim bifanaynu nictav ve-echad
omer bifanay nechtam.
One right
says
פסול, Pasul, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda... says it's okay. So X,
X, and then מחלוקת, Machlokes, basically.
מחלוקת. Machlokes. And then back to אחד אומר בפני נכתב. Echad omer
bifanay nictav. Now another case. No, no. אחד אומר בפני נכתב
ושנים אומרים,
Echad omer bifanay
nictav u-shnayim omrim, right, two, then everyone
says
כשר. Kasher. Okay.
That's our משנה. Mishnah. Now we're going to analyze it.
Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
All right. אמר רב שמואל בר יהודה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav
Shmuel bar Yehuda amar Rabbi Yochanan לא שנו אלא שאין הגט יוצא
מתחת ידי שניהם. Lo shanu ela she-ein ha-get yotze mitachat yadei shneyhem.
So
remember these are two guys here, each one is only doing a
half a job so to
speak. They did the בפני נכתב Bifanay nictav and ואחד אומר בפני
נחתם. ve-echad omer bifanay nechtam. So you have two people, which seems
to sort of be better, but they're each saying half a thing,
which is
worse.
So our משנה Mishnah is saying פסול. Pasul. Now we're going to
get into why.
But anyway he's saying is whatever, forget the why for a moment,
but the case is this guy's the main guy, the other guy's
sort of there for the ride. So he's just there and he's
able to testify to half of it. But if they were both
appointed שליחים, Shlichim, which is basically what it means, like
רש"י מתחת ידי ששניהם אדוקים בו ושניהם שליחים, mitachat yadei she-shneyhem adukim
bo u-shneyhem shlichim, they're both sent along. Then that'd be fine. אבל
גט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם, Aval get yotzei mi-tachas yedei shneichem, now
we turn the דף daf to the עמוד ב, amud bet, כשר,
kasher,
okay? So it would be fine. So אמר קסבר שנים שהביאו גט
ממדינת הים אין צריכים שיאמרו בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם.
Amar kasavar shnayim sheheviu get mimedinas hayam ein tzrichim sheyomru
b'fanai nechtav uv'fanai nechtam. So the תקנה takkana was only if one
guy brings it, right? המביא גט ממדינת הים שיאמר בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם. Hameivi get mimedinas hayam sheyomar b'fanai nechtav uv'fanai nechtam. One guy
does it, but if two guys do it, it's good, you're fine.
So now, why would that be? So we're going to get to
it, but if you remember this is basically going to harken
back to a מחלוקת machlokes of רבא Rava and רבה. Rabbah.
So remember that?
The מחלוקת machlokes of רבא Rava and
רבה. Rabbah. So it's the first משנה, mishna, yeah, the first גמרא
gemara at the first עמוד. amud.
So the two reasons that we advanced and now we're going to
see how this all plays out was that אתיא לאחלופי בקיום
שטרות, atya l'achlufi b'kiyum shetaros,
you know עלמא, alma,
right? Essentially, you know, because you don't have שיערות, shiyarus, right? You
know,
the עדים מצויים לקיימו, edim m'tzuyamin l'kaymo,
that's the רבה Rabbah thing. And then if, so what? And then
basically the problem would be, you know, if we
end up then saying like, oh, if
we're מיקל, meikel, right? If we don't have עדים מצויים לקיימו, edim
m'tzuyamin l'kaymo, then you have a whole idea of like, well what
about one
person? Okay, we're lenient by one person. But what about the fact
that oh wait,
if we're saying by one person and this is a שטר, shtar,
what about other
things
that are a שטר? shtar? You normally need two. That's why this
guy needs to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, b'fanai nechtav uv'fanai nechtam,
right? You know, that was the whole thing. Remember that? So and
רבה Rabbah says, you know, it's the לשמה lishma issue, right? You
know, you have to say that because otherwise how would you know
that it's written לשמה. lishma. So those are the two cases that,
you know, we end up also saying that even רבה Rabbah holds
from רבא, Rava, but anyway, those are those are the two ideas.
Anyway, so he holds that if it's two people you don't have
to worry about this. אמר ליה אביי אם אטא סיפא, Amar lei
abayei im ata seifa, you know the סיפא, seifa, or rather a
second case, not like the סיפא סיפא seifa seifa but
case
number two over here, right? שנים אומרים בפני נכתב ואחד אומר בפני
נחתם פסול רבי יהודה מכשיר, Shnayim omrim b'fanai nechtav v'echad omer b'fanai
nechtam pasul Rabbi Yehuda machshir, that's this case.
So we see the same thing, טעמא דאין הגט יוצא מתחת ידי
שניהם הא גט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם מכשרי רבנן. Tama d'ein haget
yotzei mi-tachas yedei shneichem ha get yotzei mi-tachas yedei shneichem machshir rabbanan.
So would you say also that's the case that these are not
both שלוחים. shluchim.
So if you... if you said this case would be good, so
certainly this case should be good, right? There's three people. So
would you say the same thing? He says אמר ליה אין. Amar
lei in. Yeah, of course. So this is his question
now: וכי אין הגט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם במאי פליגי. Vechi ein
haget yotzei mi-tachas yedei shneichem b'mai palgi.
So why... so if they're really not, you know, if these guys
are really for the ride, why is he basic... what's the סברא
sevara of רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda... Why would he say it's okay?
That's what he's saying, במאי פליגי. b'mai palgi. What is the basis?
He really needs it's more a question of רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda
I can understand why the רבנן rabbanan would say it's no good,
but why רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says it is good. What is
he thinking?
So, מר סבר גזרינן דילמא אתי לאחלופי בקיום שטרות דעלמא בעד אחד
ומר סבר לא גזרינן. Mar savar gazrinan dilma asi l'achlufi b'kiyum shetaros
d'alma b'ed echad u-mar savar lo gazrinan. So
remember, if you have two people for a שטר, shtar, it's good
to begin with, right?
If you don't, that's what he's saying.
So רבי יהודה... Rebbi Yehuda so we can understand why this would
be a problem according to everybody, right? The first...
the only guy, you only have really one person for each part
of it, right?
So you know פסול. pasul. But the question is, what about this
side? You actually have two, right?
So then would you say that it should be fine because you
have two? So we're not worried about... we're not worried about you
then getting confused about the first case and applying it to regular
קיום שטרות kiyum shetaros with one person when you... you know, so
he says
this is fine. I'm not going to go this distance because of
something else. So רבי יהודה... Rebbi Yehuda no פליג plig essentially. So
that's why you
have to say both בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם b'fanai nechtav uv'fanai nechtam
to make it really different, something
you don't have to do on a regular שטר. shtar. So מר
סבר לא גזרינן. mar savar lo gazrinan. Fine, that's version number one.
לשנא אחרינא אמר ליה אמר רב שמואל בר יהודה אמר רבי יוחנן
אפילו גט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם פסול.
Lishna acharina amar lei amar rav shmuel bar yehuda amar Rabbi
Yochanan afilu get yotzei mi-tachas yedei shneichem pasul. Even if both of
them are, you know, appointed שלוחים, shluchim, it'd still be a problem.
אמר קסבר שנים שמביאים גט. Amar kasavar shnayim she-mevi’im get. אמר ליה
אביי *amar lei Abaye* אלא מעתה *ela me'ata* סיפא דקתני *seifa dkatani*
שנים אומרים בפני נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נחתם פסול ורבי יהודה מכשיר
machshir *shnayim omrim befanai nechtav ve'echad omer befanai nechtam pasul veRabi Yehuda
machshir* אפילו גט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם פסלי רבנן Rabbanan, *afilu get
yotzei mitachat yedei shneihem pasli rabanan*. So
basically
taking the opposite tack. Remember, now this case is starting from no
matter what it's פסול *pasul*, right? Even if they're both charged with
bringing a גט *get*. So case number one, they're both charged with
it, פסול *pasul*. Case number two, three people, charged to bring a
גט *get*, still
the רבנן Rabbanan *rabanan* say it's פסול *pasul*, even if it יוצא
מתחת ידי שניהם *yotzei mitachat yedei shneihem*. אמר ליה אין *amar lei
in*. So במאי קמיפלגי kamiflagi. *bemai kamifligi*? Then what, why again, if
we're going to be so strict, then why is רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda *Rabi Yehuda* being lenient? מר סבר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה lishmah.
ומר סבר לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו *mar savar lefi she'ein beki'in
lishma umar savar lefi she'ein edim metzuyin lekaymo*. So it depends if
you hold of whether it's the problem of לשמה lishmah, *lishma* or
versus עדים מצויין לקיימו *edim metzuyin lekaymo*.
So how would that work? This is the מחלוקת machlokes?
*machloket* of רבה Rabbah
*Rabba* and רבא Rava *Rava*. Yeah, we're going to get to that
in just a second. So basically, I think
we're going to get to this, but the point is, the תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma* holds that רבנן Rabbanan *rabanan* whatever, because it's לפי
שאין בקיאין לשמה lishmah, *lefi she'ein beki'in lishma*. So that's why he
still needs to say it, right? Like if it's a לשמה lishmah.
*lishma* problem, if you don't have the same people, same both parts
of it, right, then you've sort
of missed the point, right? But no, if it's an עדים מצויין
לקיימו *edim metzuyin lekaymo*, then yeah, you have it, you have enough
people, right? You have two people in this part that are fine.
So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabi Yehuda* would say it's okay. So
you get that?
Yeah, I'm sort
of going a little fast.
No, you can go.
Okay. Should I go for it? No. Okay, I'm following. All right,
fine. So now, I mean, what it seems like is
we're reading in the מחלוקת אמוראים *machloket amora'im* into מחלוקת תנאים *machloket
tanna'im*, right? If that's what we're saying our משנה *mishna* is based
on, which is strange. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
basically saying: לימא דרבה ורבא תנאי היא *leima deRabba veRava tanna'i hi*?
So is it really a מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tanna'i*? So לא *lo*,
רבה Rabbah *Rabba* explains the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* and רבא Rava
*Rava* said... so anyway, so רבה *Rabba* will say that, meaning
we don't want to say it's sometimes we want to say it's
a מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tanna'im*, sometimes we don't. I mean like, because
if it's really מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tanna'im*, then what are רבה *Rabba*
and רבא Rava *Rava* doing, right? It's already מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tanna'im*,
what do they add to it?
And this started with רבה *Rabba* versus רבא *Rava*, right, not with
תנאים *tanna'im*.
Right. So now we're trying to say that it doesn't necessarily need
to be a מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tanna'im*. So רבא *Rava*, who is
the whole עדים מצויין לקיימו *edim metzuyin lekaymo*, can go like we
said the
first
case,
again we had two ways, like we approached it that about whether
it's גט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם *get yotzei mitachat yedei shneihem* or
not. That was like the first case. It would be a problem
if it isn't, it would be okay if it is. So רבא
*Rava* would hold like the first גט *get*, that if two people
brought it, then everyone would say it's fine.
So you don't have a problem of עדים *edim*, right? Two people
are actually bringing it, it's okay. So
our problem is only one person does it. So then רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda? *Rabi Yehuda* would say what he said before, that it's
okay, and
then in this case, because you have two others, and so now
you have עדים מצויין לקיימו *edim metzuyin lekaymo*, then the other first
one will say that it's no, it's still a problem because then
you'll start
to confuse it with other cases. But it's all one thing, right?
In other words, it's not לשמה lishmah. *lishma* versus עדים מצויין לקיימו
*edim metzuyin lekaymo*. You can operate all within one principle, right? So
רבא *Rava* explains that they're all operating in the עדים מצויין לקיימו
*edim metzuyin lekaymo* case, and then the question is how far are
you going to extend it? Is it even to a case that
it's three people or not? But again, but if they're both charged
with
or all three, whatever, are charged with bringing it, then you're fine.
It's only when like they're sort of splitting their splitting up and
they're not all charged they're coming together but they're all not
all
charged, as I was saying. Do you get that? Like, in other
words, רבא *Rava*, it's a מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tanna'im* but not on
one principle versus the other. רבא *Rava* is saying that it's מחלוקת
תנאים *machloket tanna'im* as to how far you go to apply the
principle, right? But it's still the same principle. It's not לשמה lishmah.
*lishma* versus עדים מצויין לקיימו *edim metzuyin lekaymo*. Does that make sense?
In other words, I'll say it one more time. רבא *Rava* is
saying they're both רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabi Yehuda* and the תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma*. Are operating in his principle. It's just do you
say that like in this case, this is fine because you have
עדות בחותמיו מתקיימת eidus b'chosmav miskayemes or do you say that no
because this will be a problem because it'll come to this case,
right, that you don't have and this case will come then to
basically be applied to regular שטר shtar cases with just one person.
And since the person isn't saying, this one person isn't saying the
whole thing, right, you'll start to get confused in a regular שטר
shtar case. But they're all
dealing
with the עדות בחותמיו מתקיימת eidus b'chosmav miskayemes, case. So you don't,
so it's not a רבא versus רבה thing. That's what רבא will
say. And then
so we just, we read that one little line.
So רבא would say like we just said in you know the
first version of it. And רבה אמר לך amar lach דכולי עלמא
בעינן לשמה. d'chulei alma ba'inan lishmah. No, I'm going to hold that
both the רבנן, תנא קמא, whatever you want to call them, and
רבי יהודה are both disagreeing in a case of they both hold,
they both hold you need לשמה. lishmah, That's the operating principle. So
then what's the מחלוקת? והכא במאי עסקינן ve'hacha b'mai askinan לאחר
שלמדו le'achar she'lamdu וגזירה שמא יחזור דבר לקלקולו u'gezeirah shema yachzor davar
l'kilkulo קמיפלגי. So okay, so you know originally this whole גזירה gezeirah
about saying בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם b'fani nechtav u'b'fani nechtam was because
of לשמה, lishmah but then eventually you know everyone understood this. So
now we worry that things will revert to the way it was
before, that
people
won't be, you know, saying what they need to be saying, that
so basically,
so
רבי
יהודה would say it's fine and not for you, and he would
say that
we're
talking about, no, everyone already knows. So we're not really worried because
people know it's לשמה, lishmah right? By now everyone knows
it's לשמה. lishmah, So I should be, because again the problem was,
oh, people won't know that it has to be written לשמה. lishmah,
But now everyone does know it's לשמה. lishmah, So רבי יהודה can
say, okay, you know, so you don't have to say בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם, b'fani nechtav u'b'fani nechtam, right? So he's going to be
lenient in this case, right? It's already three people, everyone already knows
לשמה, lishmah I'm not worried people are going to start to think
again that you don't have to do לשמה lishmah, because by now
everyone knows you have to do לשמה lishmah, so I'm okay. That's
what רבי יהודה is saying. I'm not worried that it's going to,
you know,
revert to the bad state that it was before. Right? So no
matter what, I mean he can actually go either way, right? If
it's a matter of עדות בחותמיו מתקיימת, you certainly have even at
this stage alone two people. If it's a matter of לשמה, lishmah,
everyone knows it's לשמה, right? So we're not, so he's totally fine.
But the רבנן are hold גזרינן gazrinan ומר סבר לא גזרינן, u'mar
savar lo gazrinan, right? So no, like you know if you don't
say, if one person is saying בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, b'fani nechtav
u'b'fani nechtam, even though everyone knows לשמה, I'm just, I'm worried about
recidivism, right? You know, I'm worried that like people are going to
start to get all messed up, people are going to, you know,
this guy's not going to say, you know, this if we split
it up then people are going to start to get confused all
over again. That's why we just instituted stay בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם,
b'fani nechtav u'b'fani nechtam, one guy saying more than he needs to
say, going there to for sure highlight the fact that this is
a לשמה concern. So רבנן are holding that that's our concern and
they're worried it's going to then you know open the floodgates so
to speak. Now what's the, I'll ask the גמרא's Gemara question if
you don't ask it yourselves. So now
theoretically, right, so רבי יהודה holds that this is good, right, because
everyone knows it's לשמה, we're not worried. So what should he also
be doing?
רבי יהודה disagreed in this case, right? What about the first case,
right? He should disagree just as much, right? If they all know
לשמה, right, then you know why should this not be a problem?
I mean why should this be a problem according to רבי יהודה?
Everyone understands, already going to go back and whatever, once we're worried
we're worried in this case, we're worried in that case, it seems
a little bit extreme but whatever it is we're worried, right? רבי
יהודה says no we're not worried at all, right? Okay, we're not
worried and then this should be good too, right? Why is he
not disagreeing over here in the first case, right? If you're not
worried, everyone knows it's לשמה, that's our concern, and by now everyone
knows and he's not worried that things will revert, so
why
isn't he disagreeing?
So that's what the גמרא's asking, וליפלוג נמי רבי יהודה ברישא. v'liflog
nami Rebbi Yehuda b'reisha.
So why should he not disagree in the first case too? Everyone's
with me? Good? Good? Yeah? Okay, I want to make sure you
know I don't want to you know, we have time so I
can explain. No then, okay, okay, all right. הא איתמר עלה אמר
עולא חלוק היה רבי יהודה אף בראשונה. ha itamar alah amar Ulla
chaluk hayah Rebbi Yehuda af b'rishona. He actually does disagree on the
first case. Okay. So though, so basically when רבי יהודה מכשיר, Rebbi
Yehuda machshir, it's not reinterpreting it like you know it... what it
means is רבי יהודה מכשיר, Rebbi Yehuda machshir, he means in both
cases, right? Sometimes you have case, you know, you have ruling one
and then ruling two and then a disagreement and we don't know
if the disagreement is on both parts, right? Is he just disagreeing
on the second part which is the way we originally thought? Or
is he disagreeing on... it's the same thing, right? תנא קמא *Tanna
Kamma* says פסול פסול *Pasul
Pasul*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says כשר kasher. כשר *Kasher Kasher*. So
that's the way he would interpret it.
It's kind of strange because he's coming up with that without a
ברייתא *Baraita*.
Because all of a sudden an אמורא
*Amora*...
מתני רב אושעיה
לעולא *Matni Rav Oshaya le-Ulla* רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* בזו ולא באחרת
*b-zu ve-lo b-acheret*. Right? We do have a
apparently this is like a ruling ברייתא *Baraita* somewhere, right? רבי יהודה
מכשיר machshir בזו *Rabbi Yehuda Machshir b-zu*. It says, it says, it
says, okay, so רבי
יהודה מכשיר בזו ולא באחרת *Rabbi Yehuda Machshir b-zu ve-lo b-acheret*, right?
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says oh this case is good and not
the other, right?
So the question is what is this, right? Remember we have three
parts over here, right?
So what we tried to say is, what we tried to say
a second before, right, before we just had this ברייתא *Baraita*, is
really רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* disagrees in both of these cases. But
now we have a ברייתא *Baraita* says he's מכשיר *Machshir* in this
and not the other. So it's not the other this case just
to
say what this and this is, right? So what we're assuming is
that the other that he's not מכשיר *Machshir* on, right, would be
the first case. And
we just tried saying a second ago that logically he's not worried
about
the דבר החוזר לקלקולו *Davar ha-Chozer le-Kilkulo*, they should be מכשיר *Machshir*
in the first case. Now it seems that he isn't, right? So
then why isn't he? He should be saying it's okay. לא לאתויי
בפני נחתם *Lo le-atuyei Bifnei Nechtam*. That's it, like
the other I mean, you know, בפני *Bifnei* it could be another
case, right? Let's say one just says בפני נחתם *Bifnei Nechtam*,
right? That's it. That's all he's saying. בפני נחתם *Bifnei Nechtam*. A
single witness. A single witness, right? אבל לא בפני נכתב *Aval lo
Bifnei Nechtav*, right? He's only saying so one guy only says half
the part. So that's what he's not מכשיר *Machshir* on, right? Because
it can't be this, because everyone agrees with over here, right? And
then it should be
both of
these if we're saying that, you know, he's not worried about דבר
החוזר לקלקולו *Davar ha-Chozer le-Kilkulo*, so it has to be another case.
So the case is not in our משנה
*Mishnah*, the zero one one. Yeah, exactly. It'd be like sort of
like it'd be, yeah, it'd be zero בפני נכתב *Bifnei Nechtav* and
then one, right? That's strange. So everyone says פסול *Pasul* at all
presumably. Okay?
So this would be case one, case two,
case three.
All this is in our משנה *Mishnah*.
This is something else, right? This would be our
תוספתא *Tosefta*.
Well, this is the גמרא *Gemara* interpreting.
Yes. Well, no, I understand. But this is where we are right
now, right?
סלקא דעתך אמינא
*Salka
Daatach Amina*.
So why would we have thought otherwise? הואיל ולא גזר רבי יהודה
גזירה שמא יחזור דבר לקלקולו *Hoil ve-lo Gazar Rabbi Yehuda Gzeira shema
yachzor Davar le-Kilkulo*, since he's not worried about this recidivism, as I
like to say this, זו מה אתו לאוקמי קיום שטרות דעלמא *Zu
Ma Atu le-Okmei Kiyum Shtarot d-Alma*, so maybe ועדי אחד לא נמי
לא גזר
*ve-edei echad lo nami lo gazar*. So maybe we'd say alright fine,
so you know, so remember like we're not worried about there are
two concerns, right? About לשמה *Lishma* and עדים שבפני נכתב *Eidim she-Be-fanai
Nikhtav*, and then you know do we say that we're going to
eventually come to confuse this application where we're being more מיקל *Meikel*
with one guy to regular קיום שטרות *Kiyum Shtarot* where we really
need two people? So since he's not worried about this part, remember
all going according to the לשמה *Lishma* problem, right? Remember that? Like
you know we had two ways of interpreting it, like you know
that so that it's not a מחלוקת תנאים *Machloket Tannaim*. רבא *Rava*
can say, you know, what he said in this whole second part
here is according to רבא *Rava*, right? So okay, but remember
as we ended up saying, רבא *Rava* holds like רבא *Rava*, right?
So he still would hold that it's a problem of עדים שבפני
נכתב *Eidim she-Be-fanai Nikhtav* and regular קיום שטרות *Kiyum Shtarot*, and he
also holds it's a problem of לשמה *Lishma*. So he's got out
of the לשמה *Lishma* problem, so he might say alright well he's
not worried about לשמה *Lishma*, maybe he's not also worried about עדים
שבפני נכתב *Eidim she-Be-fanai Nikhtav*? Maybe he'd say this is also good?
No, קא משמע לן *Kamashma Lan* it doesn't go that far. He
still, even with that, he would be saying,
you know, that I'm not going to go all the way, I'm
not going to hold there are no problems, right? I'm not worried
about recidivism, but I still hold that it's a problem about confusing
it with a regular שטר *Shtar*. So therefore in this last case,
you're only doing half the job, he's not going to say
that you can do that.
איתמר נמי אמר רבי יהודה
*Itmar Nami Amar Rabbi Yehuda* שניים ששיגרו *Shnayim she-Shigru* As to
how far, as to how far we go over here, that
it's a case of שנים שהביאו that באנו למחלוקת
רבי יהודה ורבנן, banu le-machloket Rabbi Yehuda ve-rabbanan, right? So that's how
you interpret that, meaning like this case. The point of saying that
is this case is totally not, right? It's only in this case,
like you know, two people, however you divide that up. But a
case of one person only doing half a job, רבי יהודה לא
הוה מכשיר, Rabbi Yehuda lo hava machshir, right?
That's so meaning that's the other thing that
we said, oh, רבי יהודה מכשיר בזו ולא בזו. Rabbi Yehuda machshir
be-zo ve-lo be-zo. So that's the other thing that Rabbi Yehuda is
not מכשיר on. That is the thing that Rabbi Yehuda is not
being מכשיר on. But not one of these cases, because you know
we said that Rabbi Yehuda would say it's כשר. Does that make
sense?
Alright, and this is a good place to stop, I mean because
this like a next, this is the next topic.
So we're up to רבה בר בר חנה. Rabbah bar bar Chana.
Yeah,
okay, that's what we're up to.
That's where I'm stopping. Right, okay, alright,
okay.
I mean, I guess I could have gone to the two dots,
but you know. We'll go, no, I mean actually, I really stopped
early. I didn't know how far, I thought this would take longer.
So,
thank you. Alright, take care everyone. Until tomorrow.